<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>programming on</title><link>https://georgek.github.io/blog/categories/programming/</link><description>Recent content in programming on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://georgek.github.io/blog/categories/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Working on Multiple Web Projects with Docker Compose and Traefik</title><link>https://georgek.github.io/blog/posts/multiple-web-projects-traefik/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2023 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://georgek.github.io/blog/posts/multiple-web-projects-traefik/</guid><description>Docker Compose is a brilliant tool for bringing up local development environments for web projects. But working with multiple projects can be a pain due to clashes. For example, all projects want to listen to port 80 (or perhaps one of the super common higher ones like 8000 etc.). This forces developers to only bring one project up at a time, or hack the compose files to change the port numbers.</description></item><item><title>My 2023 Emacs Python Setup</title><link>https://georgek.github.io/blog/posts/emacs-python-2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 14:19:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://georgek.github.io/blog/posts/emacs-python-2023/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been using Emacs for almost 15 years now. Somewhat surprisingly, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t touched my config in three years! It&amp;rsquo;s been working that well. But now that Emacs 29 has been released I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to take a look at what&amp;rsquo;s new and there have been some big changes, particularly for Python.
Goodbye Elpy, Goodbye Projectile Elpy has been the primary mode for Python development for me for years now. But sadly, it looks like the project is no more.</description></item><item><title>Arduino Programming with Emacs</title><link>https://georgek.github.io/blog/posts/emacs-arduino/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://georgek.github.io/blog/posts/emacs-arduino/</guid><description>If you want to start Arduino programming you&amp;rsquo;ll notice a lot of the documentation and tutorials are centred around the Arduino IDE. Now, obviously, as an Emacs user you&amp;rsquo;ll be loath to install something like Arduino IDE, let alone actually use it. The good news is it&amp;rsquo;s super easy to get started with Arduino with any editor, including Emacs and even Vim if you so desire.
All the Arduino IDE is doing is calling a cross-compiler toolchain then using avrdude to communicate with the Arduino to upload software.</description></item></channel></rss>